All right, we're going to start because it's already late.
All right, good morning everybody. Today's ט"ו באב Tu B'Av and appropriately
today's דף Daf
is לב, Lamed Bais,
לב. Lev. So go figure.
We pick up on the
משנה Mishnah on לא עמוד ב'.
Lamed Aleph Amud Bais. Wait, what happened to לב? Lamed Bais? We
made it up on שבת. Shabbat. Yeah, so now we're on track.
Let's try to stay on it. So חמץ שנפלה עליו מפולת, Chametz
shenaphlah alav mapolet, first
of the משניות Mishnayot
on לא עמוד
ב'
Lamed Aleph
Amud
Bais is where we're picking up.
So, you know, this חמץ chametz now got buried by rubble. הרי
הוא כמבוער, Harei hu kimevuar, so it's considered that you've done your
job. Can't get to it anyway. רבן גמליאל Rabban Gamliel says he
has a little bit more of a higher criteria. כל שאין הכלב
יכול לחפש אחריו. Kol she'ein hakelev yakhol lachapes acharav. So it depends.
Just the mere fact that this is buried is not sufficient, but
if it's buried deep enough that a dog will not be able
to unearth it, then that's considered מבוער. mevuar. אמר רב חסדא, Amar
Rav Chisda, צריך שיבטל בלבו. Tzarich sheyevatel belibo. Nevertheless, רב חסדא Rav
Chisda said that you have to still do a ביטול bitul and
as it's not explained as to why, but רש"י Rashi explains, you
can just look at it now. שמא יפקח הגל Shema yipaka’ach hagal
because maybe somehow this rubble will be unearthed, you know, someone will
move it away במועד be-Moed ונמצא עובר עליו. venimtza over alav. And
then, you know, now you're עובר over because the point is לא
יראה לך ולא ימצא לך. lo yeira'eh lekha velo yimatzei lekha. And
now it's מצוי matzui because it's I guess it was intact enough
that removing the stones, you know, it's not like crushed and smushed
and into all little pieces. So and now you're עובר over on
it, which is very interesting. You know, you thought you'd done enough
and then it turns out you haven't. So that's why you have
to do the ביטול bitul because as we have mentioned already that
מן התורה min HaTorah ביטול bitul is enough. So okay, תנא, tanna,
כמה חפיסת הכלב? Kama chapisat hakelev? How much can it go? שלשה
טפחים. Sheloshah tephachim. So three טפחים. tephachim. It can go, it can
dig three טפחים tephachim deep. So according to the opinion of רבן
שמעון בן גמליאל. Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel. How many inches? I guess
this is a טפח, tephach, I guess. Right? So three of these.
Nine to twelve depending on the thing. No, a big dog could
really dig up... I was going to say that. A big dog
would definitely be able to... mine could.
Yeah, the big big dog...
big big holes. All right, that's true. But in those days the
dogs
kind of regressed to the mean.
They didn't have breeds, so the average mean is about thirty
pounds and kind of
tawny,
and that's what they boarded out
and that's where they walked about.
Fair enough. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי, Amar
lei Rav Acha berei deRav Yosef leRav Ashi, הא דאמר שמואל כספים
אין להן שמירה אלא
בקרקע.
Hada de'amar Shmuel kesaphim ein lahen
shemirah ela be-karka. So bringing in a different teaching.
So let's say someone entrusts you with money. So what's the best
way to watch it?
So according to this, the best way to do it is bury
it.
So מי בעינן שלשה טפחים עליו?
Mee ba'inan sheloshah tephachim alav? So now that we're saying that you
may have
introduced a criteria of three טפחים tephachim to have the
חמץ chametz considered to be essentially buried, you know, inaccessible, so the
same thing for כספים, kesaphim, if you're going to put
it in
the ground, you need to dig three טפחים tephachim deep or not?
אמר ליה, Amar lei, הכא משום ריחא בעינן שלשה טפחים. Hacha mishum
reicha ba'inan sheloshah tephachim. No, the reason here is because a dog...
and maybe the dog will be able to dig more than three
טפחים, tephachim, but it's not going to dig for what it can't
smell. So presumably over here anyway, they're saying that below three טפחים,
tephachim, it's not going to be able to smell it anyway, so
it's not going to dig for it. That makes sense. I'm surprised
רב אשי Rav Ashi should ask such a... No, but his question
was about... no, no, wait. So that's okay. But התם Hatam in
the case of money, משום אכסויי מעינא הוא, mishum ikhsoyyei me-ayna hu,
so that's just to get it out of people's sight. ולא בעינן
שלשה. ve-lo ba'inan sheloshah. So you don't need three טפחים. tephachim. It's
just enough that people won't be able to see it anymore. So
they go holey, put it in some earth and once it's I
guess do it and smooth it out in such a way people
aren't going to be able to know that you've
dug a hole for your money, but you don't need to dig
it so deep.
וכמה? Ve-khamma? So then how much should you dig? Because the statement
still was you have to bury it in the earth. אמר רב
אפרם בר פפא, Amar Rav'afram bar Pappa, מסיכרא טפח. mishikra tephach. Just
one טפח. tephach. So for חמץ chametz it's three according to that
opinion in the גמרא, Gemara, by the way, of רבן שמעון בן
גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel and that wasn't necessarily agreed upon. I
mean רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel may be explaining
the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma or may be disagreeing with him. מסיכרא,
Mishikra, רש"י Rashi says ממקום פלוני. mimmakom ploni. Yeah, that's רב אפרם
בר פפא Rav'afram bar Pappa was one of these people בר פפא.
bar Pappa. We say all ten of them at the end of
the סיום, Siyum, we go through ten of them. So I guess
he lived in סיכרא, Sikhra, maybe there's another רב אפרם בר פפא.
Rav'afram bar Pappa. What does that have to do with סיכרא? Sakhra?
You you do... No, he's from סיכרא. Sakhra. So he said טפח.
tefach.
Because for money, it's not about a dog smelling it, it doesn't
really care to...
Right, it's coin. Right. It's just so people won't know that the
money's hidden. What's... why should there be a difference of place? This
is not הלכה. halacha.
No, סיכרא, Sakhra, he just happens to be from סיכרא.
Sakhra. You're saying like you know the New York rabbi said... סיכרא.
Sakhra. Yeah. Actually there is this הלכה. halacha. No, no, I'm saying
the סיכרא Sakhra has nothing... it's not part of the...
saying in סיכרא. Sakhra. No, no, he's saying he's
from סיכרא Sakhra and then he said a טפח. tefach. So, so
that's the difference. Okay.
So האוכל תרומת חמץ בפסח,
ha'ochel
terumat
chametz bePesach, now separate topic. So now, let's say don't look
at the משנה Mishnah yet, actually, although
I started it,
but I shouldn't
have.
So, so תרומה, terumah, there are a number of things, right, you're
not allowed on פסח, Pesach, and especially חמץ chametz is one of
them, and we already learned that once the חג chag starts, it's
the תורה Torah sort of takes it out of your possession, right?
And we also know that there's certain, there's certain things that you're
allowed to have, like let's say הקדש hekdesh stuff, it's not considered
yours, right? שלך אי אתה רואה אבל אתה רואה של אחרים ושל
גבוה. shelcha i atta ro'eh aval atta ro'eh shel acherim veshel gavoah.
We're allowed to see חמץ chametz of נכרים nokrim and של הקדש.
veshel hekdesh. We learned that too. Now, תרומה. terumah. תרומה terumah is
not הקדש, hekdesh, but it's sort of in the, in the world
of קדשים. kodshim. Now, תרומה terumah is also one of these things
you can't eat that that's חמץ, chametz, because the תרומה terumah is
given to the כהן, kohen, right? And as opposed to הקדש hekdesh
stuff, which is, you know, some parts maybe burnt on the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, לחם הפנים lechem hapanim is sort of God's, but then it's
also given to the כהן, kohen, that'd be הקדש חמץ hekdesh chametz
stuff, essentially. הקדש hekdesh is also something I מקדישed. makdish I מקדישed
makdish this loaf, whatever reason, you know, he may sell the value
of it and whatever. But so that's הקדש hekdesh stuff, but now
if I were, if I were to ask you, well what happened,
if this כהן kohen had תרומה terumah and the תרומה terumah is
חמץ, chametz, and then a, someone ate it on פסח. Pesach. Would
you need to give him, make any restitution to him or not?
What would you think?
Just it's an איסור כרת issur karet to eat חמץ chametz on
פסח.
Pesach. Exactly, that's it. So you say what's, what's the point, right?
Why are we worrying about making restitution
to the
כהן, kohen, you know?
The כהן kohen doesn't really own it anymore. Right. You'd say either
it's a כרת, karet, so maybe קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim lei
b'drabbah minei, right? So be bitter, basically bigger things to worry about,
he's already going to be killed, so who cares about making restitution.
Or you can say, like Charlie did, either you know, the חמץ
chametz is worthless anyway, right? Forget about כרת karet for a moment,
what are you paying him for? Yeah. Okay. Well, surprisingly, that's, that's
why I asked you what you'd think, our משנה Mishnah says האוכל
תרומת חמץ בפסח בשוגג משלם קרן וחומש במזיד פטור מתשלומין ומדמי עצים.
ha'ochel terumat chametz bePesach beshogeg meshaleim keren vechomesh bemezid
patur mitashlumin umidmei etzim. So if you eat it בשוגג, beshogeg, so
what happens if you eat normal תרומה terumah mistakenly? What do you
have to do? Give it
back and pay a
חומש. chomesh.
You don't have to bring the קרבן? korban? Well, you do too,
but,
but in terms
of, you do that, but the כהן kohen though, the כהן kohen
will get get more than he started out with essentially. And what
happens if you eat it במזיד? bemezid? What'd you just say? What
happens if you
eat it במזיד? bemezid? Karet. Right, you got a,
well not כרת, karet, but I think it's מיתה בידי שמים.
misah biydei shamayim.
So yeah, right. It's what? מיתה בידי שמים. misah biydei shamayim.
I mean, they're both death at the hands
of heaven, but one is כרת, karet, the other's just מיתה בידי
שמים. misah biydei shamayim. The גמרא Gemara in other places goes to
the differences between כרת karet and מיתה בידי שמים. misah biydei shamayim.
כרת karet may also mean that, like, you know, if you didn't
have children you will no longer, or if you did, they may
die at a younger age. But מיתה בידי שמים, misah biydei shamayim,
you know, you're just killed off, and not necessarily any other impact
to your family. So I mean you're still dying at the hands
of heaven, but, but yeah. כרת karet you don't get... Right, that,
that too. But, but anyway, they're slightly different. You know, again, the
differences are not discussed over here. But basically, what this משנה Mishnah
is saying then, is that the same law applies, right? That's what
we just, that's what we just determined. So the question is why,
right? You'd think that based on what we just said, it shouldn't.
So if you just look at, if you look at רש״י, Rashi,
he says interesting, so when we, eat it בשוגג, beshogeg, this is
all vis-a-vis the תרומה terumah part. שגג בתרומה, shagag biterumah, you didn't
know it was תרומה, terumah, or you know, that's whatever, that's your
case. ואפילו הזיד בחמץ. ve'afillu hezid bechametz. Even if you ate, even
if you said, I know this is חמץ, chametz, I know this
is פסח, Pesach, I'm eating it anyway, but just didn't know it
was תרומה. terumah. Even then, משלם קרן וחומש. meshaleim keren vechomesh. ואף
על גב דלא הוי שוה מידי, ve'af al gav d'la havei shaveh
midei, which is Charlie's other objection, it's not really worth anything, the
חמץ chametz of פסח Pesach is אסור בהנאה. asur behana'ah. מיהו שוגג
בתרומה דכתיב ביה ובחמישתו יוסף עליו ונתן לכהן את הקדש, mihu shagag
biterumah dechtiv beih ubechamishito yosef alav venatan lacohen et hakodesh, הדבר הראוי
להיות קודש שאינו יכול לשלם לו מעות
hadavar hara'uy lihyot kodesh she'eino yachol
lishalem lo ma'ot אלא פירות ella peirot והתשלומין נעשים תרומה, vehatashlumin na'asim
terumah, I'll explain in a second. Anyway, the point being then, is
that I understand vis-a-vis the laws of חמץ chametz it may be
worthless, you know, you're קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kim lei b'drabbah minei,
but basically this is a law vis-a-vis תרומה. terumah. It's תרומה terumah
and it's חמץ. chametz. So okay, חמץ chametz may be a separate
issue, but nevertheless, because the law... Is a fifth zero? Is a
fifth zero? But he's saying never- he's saying that it's- that's its-
it's zero
because of
the חמץ Chometz
aspect. Because with the תרומה Terumah aspect, he still- it's- it's a
very strange law. It's a very strange law. And I don't think
you give the כהן Kohen חמץ. Chometz. No, you don't give him
חמץ. Chometz.
You give him- you give him- let's say it
was- you give him the, you know, fruit that's worth the value
of a loaf of חמץ Chometz that you- we'll get into value.
We're actually going to explain, you know, like how- basically, you give
him- you give him something else, you know, that's worth an equivalent.
How you determine equivalent is another story. So let's assume the כהן
Kohen hasn't sinned and he's nullified the חמץ.
Chometz. So it doesn't belong to anybody. Does it still
maintain its תרומה Terumah
status? Oh, that's interesting. And yeah, meaning he didn't- he didn't burn
it, which he should have done also.
Yeah, I mean that's- it doesn't seem to say that it makes
a difference, but let's, you know, let's try to figure it out
from the גמרא. Gemara. But yeah, I mean the point is, if
you want to look at it- if you want to look at
it another way, look, the מזיד, Mezid, the guy eats it up
מזיד, Mezid, right? Yes, it's קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, Kim Lei Bed'rabah
Minei, but also- the- again, the point because getting back to the
קרבן, Korban, right, if you- this is viewed as an atonement, right?
So this is how you're atoning for the fact that you violated
the sanctity of the תרומה. Terumah. See? So that's why you have
to make restitution to the כהן. Kohen. If you eat it במזיד,
Bemezid, then you're not viewed as being worthy of the atonement, so
therefore, you know, you're off. I mean, so monetarily you come out
ahead, but spiritually you come out behind. So basically, if you want
to view it in that context, you're making- if you will, restitution,
you're making whole the law that you know has now become broken
through your, you know, because you violated it. That's, I guess, if
you will, the more spiritual way of looking at it, which is
maybe what's in operation here. So not that this is really spelled
out, but this is kind of how we're trying to figure it
out. And okay, so מזיד, Mezid, you are פטור. Patur. What value
may תרומה Terumah have? It may have value, especially if it's תרומה
טמאה, Terumah Temeah, that you're allowed to use it as firewood, right?
So even then you don't have to pay the value of the-
although it may have no value as חמץ, Chometz, because you can't
really eat the חמץ, Chometz, but it may have potentially had value
as firewood, and even then you're פטור Patur for paying that. So
that's our משנה. Mishna. תנן התם האוכל תרומה בשוגג, Tenan Tam Hachol
Terumah Beshogeg, regular תרומה, Terumah, forget חמץ Chometz for the moment, בשוגג
Beshogeg משלם קרן וחומש, Meshalem Keren Vechomesh, which is essentially what happens
in our משנה. Mishna. אחד אוכל ואחד שותה, Echad Ochel Ve'echad Shoteh,
doesn't make a difference if you eat it, doesn't make a difference
if you drink it. Now we're on מ"ו ע"א. Mem-Vav Amud Aleph.
אחד סך, Echad Asach, or if you anointed yourself with it, let's
say it was, you know, תרומה Terumah oil. אחד תרומה טמאה ואחד
תרומה טהורה, Echad Terumah Temeah Ve'echad Terumah Tehorah, משלם חומש. Meshalem Chomesh.
So it doesn't make a difference, basically, what kind of תרומה Terumah
it was, as long as you've used it when you shouldn't have,
you have to pay a קרן וחומש Keren Vechomesh and also וחומש
לחומש. Vechomesh Lechomesh. And you know, this continues indefinitely. Let's say then
the value of the fifth that you used and then you, you
know, use that, then you pay- you pay that back and then
a fifth on that and then, you know, keeps on going indefinitely
until the value becomes basically meaningless. But the point is it, you
know, this continues. Yeah. איבעיא להו, Ibayu Lehu, so now, okay, this
is basically now going to- you'll see it especially on עמוד ב',
Amud Bet, we're just going to get into laws of תרומה Terumah
essentially, this is a stepping stone for that. So איבעיא להו, Ibayu
Lehu, כשהוא משלם לפי מדה משלם או לפי דמים משלם. Keshehu Meshalem
Lefi Midah Meshalem O Lefi Damim Meshalem. So basically the better way
of looking at this, just to make it easier on us to
understand, so let's say I drank- let's forget חמץ Chometz for the
moment, but let's say I drank a gallon of milk, that was
תרומה Terumah milk. Just go with it, right? תרומה Terumah oil, better,
right? I use- I used olive oil, you know, he gave him
like a liter of olive oil, and now I used it to
make my salad and saute my onions, right? So I used it.
So it's a liter of oil. But now when I pay back,
do I have to pay him back a liter of oil, or
let's say this liter is selling for, you know, for six bucks
in Costco, do I have to pay him six bucks regardless of
the fluctuation in price? Right? That's the question. You get it? So
you're paying the value or you're paying the quantity back? So, because
like, let's say now the six bucks is half a liter, so
do I give him back half a liter? Or not? Or no?
Or I just give him a liter because that's what I, you
know, I took a liter, I give back a liter. So that's
the question. So- so now, the other rule you should always remember
is that הקדש Hekdesh always comes up on the upside, right? So
we'll see that. כל היכא דמעיקרא שוי ארבעה זוזי והשתא שוי זוזא
לא תיבעי לך דודאי כמעיקרא משלם. Ka Heicha Demikara Shavei Arba Zuzei
Ve'hashta Shavei Zuza Lo Tiba'i Lach De'vadai Kemikara Meshalem. So let's say
the value went down. So let's say I stole it and it
was worth six bucks and now, you know, there's a crash in
the market for olives and a liter's worth a dollar. So certainly
no one's going to say only pay back a dollar. So the
question's only on the upside, like I stole it, it was worth-
six bucks and now it's worth twelve bucks, right? But not the
other way around. So that's what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying.
So if it was, they give the answer four and they give
the analogy of four and six, but the same rule would apply,
דהיכא דמעיקרא שויא ארבעה *d'heicha d'me'ikara shavya arba'a*. So if it was
once worth four zuz, ולבסוף שויא זוזא *u'levasof shavya zuza*, and now
it's only worth one, לא תיבעי לך דודאי כמעיקרא משלם *lo tiba'ei
lach d'vadai k'me'ikara meshalem*. So certainly I'll pay what it was worth
in the beginning, he's not going to lose out, לפי דמים lefi
damim? *lefi damim*, דלא גרע מגזלן *d'lo gara mi'gazlan*, it's not going
to be any worse than your garden variety גזלן *gazlan*, דתנן כל
הגזלנים משלמים כשעת הגזילה *d'tenan kol ha'gazlanim meshalmim k'sha'at ha'gezeilah*. You pay
the כשעת הגזילה *k'sha'at ha'gezeilah*. כי תיבעי לך דמעיקרא שוה shaveh. זוזא
ולבסוף שוה shaveh, ארבעה *ki tiba'ei lach d'me'ikara shaveh zuza u'levasof shaveh
arba'a*, the other way around. It didn't go from four to one,
it went from one to four. מאי לפי מידה midah, משלם *mai
lefi midah meshalem*? So do you pay according to the quantity? דאמר
ליה גריוא אכלת גריוא משלם *d'amar leh griva achalt griva meshalem*, basically
what, you know, as much as you eat you pay back essentially.
Actually pronounced as גריוא *griva*. So whatever it is, a particular measure,
you know, you pay back basically לפי מידה midah. *lefi midah*. So
whatever the amount you took is the amount you give back, או
דילמא לפי דמים damim. משלם זוזא אכלת זוזא משלם *o dilma lefi
damim meshalem zuza achalt zuza meshalem*? No, it's the money. I took
a zuz's worth of stuff and I pay him back a zuz's
worth of stuff, doesn't make a difference if it quadrupled in value.
אמר רב יוסף תא שמע אכל גרוגרות *amar Rav Yosef ta shema
achal grogerot*. So ושילם לו תמרים תבוא עליו ברכה *v'shileim lo tmarim
tavo alav bracha*. So you took the dried figs, right? And then
you paid him back with dates. So one is dried, basically the
תמרים *tmarim* are nice, good, fresh dates are worth more than the
figs, that's the point. So in basically an absolute terms, so these
are more valuable and תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav bracha*, you did
a great thing. So what's the story? תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav
bracha* is you did even more than you needed to. אי אמרת
בשלמא לפי מידה משלם היינו דתבוא עליו ברכה *ei amrat bishlama lefi
midah meshalem hainu d'tavo alav bracha*. So let's say I took a
liter of, you know, I ate a liter of whatever of dried
figs and I paid him back a liter of fresh dates, then
I understand, because all you needed to do was pay him back
the quantity, right? But now you're paying him back something that's not
only the same quantity but more valuable. That's why תבוא עליו ברכה
*tavo alav bracha*. Because דגריוא דגרוגרות שוה זוזא *d'griva d'grogerot shaveh zuza*
that I ate a whatever liter of גרוגרות *grogerot* which are worth
a zuz, וגריוא דתמרים שוה ארבעה *v'griva d'tmarim shaveh arba'a*. Now I
give him back the same quantity of something that's worth a lot
more. אלא אי אמרת לפי דמים damim, משלם אמאי תבוא עליו ברכה
זוזא אכל וזוזא קא משלם *ela ei amrat lefi damim meshalem amai
tavo alav bracha zuza achal v'zuza ka meshalem*? But if it was
only the value, let's say forget the quantity for a moment, if
I ate a certain amount of dried figs, I mean the value,
if I ate a certain amount of dried figs that's worth a
zuz, so presumably I've adjusted, let's say a zuz was like ten
figs and I'm paying him back in, I mean figs, ten dried
figs, and I'm paying him back in fresh dates, so I presumably
pay him fewer. I'm basically giving the same value is what their
thinking is, right? Then why תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav bracha*, you
get it? So the point is if I'm giving him back the
same quantity of something worth more, then great. But if I'm giving
him back a value, then presumably I've adjusted the value. Let's say
it was ten figs that are worth a zuz and now I
give fresh dates, so I give him one date, right? So why
תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav bracha*? I'm still paying back the same
value. What does he care if it's a fig or a date?
He's still only getting a zuz. In the first case we thought
he's actually getting more than a zuz's worth of stuff. So אמר
אביי Amar Abaye: לעולם לפי דמים damim, משלם *amar Abaye le'olam lefi
damim meshalem*. I can even explain it in a case where it's
still the value and I'm paying him back the same value, but
nevertheless תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav bracha*. So why? ואמאי תבוא עליו
ברכה משום דקא משלם ליה מידי דלא קפיץ עליה זבינא וקא משלם
ליה מידי דקפיץ עליה זבינא *v'amai tavo alav bracha mishum d'ka meshalem
leh midi d'lo kafeitz aleh zabina v'ka meshalem leh midi d'kafeitz aleh
zabina*. Because if he wants to resell it, he'll be able to
do so much more easily. People would much rather buy a fresh
date than a dried fig. So even though I paid him back
the same value, it's still worth more to him because it's easier,
not in absolute terms, it's not worth more in absolute terms but
it's worth more for him because
it'll be easier
for him to get rid of it, sell it if he wants
to. That's why תבוא עליו ברכה *tavo alav bracha*. Okay. תנן התם
*tenan hatam*, now back to חמץ chametz *chametz*, but we're going to
get back to עמוד ב' amud bet *amud bet* as I mentioned
to just general laws, we're going to discuss general laws of these
things. תנן אכל תרומת חמץ בפסח trumat chametz bePesach בשוגג be-shogeg משלם
קרן וחומש keren v'chomesh. *tenan achal trumat chametz b'Pesach b'shogeg meshalem keren
v'chomesh*. That's what we learned, right? That was our משנה *Mishnah*. He
ate תרומת חמץ trumat chametz *trumat chametz* on Pesach בשוגג be-shogeg *b'shogeg*,
no different than just any other time, he's משלם קרן keren וחומש
*meshalem keren v'chomesh*. And although there are two dots over here, it
just viewed as if they're not there because they're still trying to
figure out whether it's מידה *midah* or value. Okay. אי אמרת בשלמא
לפי מידה משלם שפיר *ei amrat bishlama lefi midah meshalem shapir*. So
I understand, right? So the laws of תרומה trumah *trumah* is that
I have to pay him back the quantity. I don't really care
about value because חמץ chametz *chametz* is worthless. So אכל תרומת חמץ
terumat chametz בפסח בשוגג be-shogeg, משלם קרן karen וחומש *achal trumat chametz
b'Pesach b'shogeg meshalem keren v'chomesh*. אי אמרת בשלמא לפי מידה משלם שפיר
*ei amrat bishlama lefi midah meshalem shapir*. I know that works out
because okay, took a whatever liter, I give him back a liter.
אלא אי אמרת לפי דמים משלם חמץ chametz. *ela ei amrat lefi
damim meshalem chametz*... פסח Pesach. בר דמים הוא? Is it worth anything?
So אין, in, yes, הא מני רבי יוסי הגלילי היא דאמר חמץ
בפסח מותר בהנאה. ha mani Rabbi Yose HaGelili hi de-amar Chametz be-Pesach
mutar be-hana'ah. Because remember, there was a מחלוקת, machloket, we had this
before, חמץ בפסח. Chametz be-Pesach. Is it worthless? Well we always think
it's worthless, but that wasn't necessarily agreed upon, right? We ended up
פסקנינג paskening like somebody, but I mean this is the other opinion,
רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili said that it actually does have
value. So therefore... I'm sorry, no, even on פסח. Pesach. Even during
פסח. Pesach, There were three opinions. One is after פסח, Pesach you
know, but another opinion is even on פסח Pesach it has value.
So it's like that opinion. Okay, so fine, according to the other
opinion you may not have. But this is according to that opinion.
Okay, but wait, אי הכי אימא סיפא ee hachi eima seifa במזיד
פטור מן התשלומין ומדמי עצים. be-mezid patur min ha-tashlumim u-mi-d'mei etzim. So
if you eat it במזיד be-mezid you're פטור patur from תשלומין tashlumim
and דמי עצים. d'mei etzim. אי רבי יוסי הגלילי אמאי פטור מן
התשלומין ומדמי עצים? ee Rabbi Yose HaGelili amai patur min ha-tashlumim u-mi-d'mei
etzim? So why should he be פטור? patur? It still has value.
So, okay, so why? Still pay him back. Why you פטור?
patur? No, but קסבר הרקנוס בן
הקנס,
ksavar Harkonus
ben
Hakanas, so this is a sort of multi-step thing. Because even though
we're saying it's mentions רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGelili, and even
though רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGelili is one of the ones
that says it does have value, which is why בשוגג you'd have
to pay him back, nevertheless במזיד be-mezid you do not, דתניא הרקנוס
בן הקנס היה עושה את יום הכיפורים כשבת לתשלומין. de-tanya Harkonus ben
Hakanas haya oseh et Yom HaKippurim ke-Shabbat le-tashlumim. So he equates, if
you will, like יום כיפור Yom Kippur to שבת Shabbat לתשלומין. le-tashlumim.
So what do we mean by that? So we basically, so the
point being, it's what we just basically said, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה.
kam lei be-drabba minei. So like it's יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, it's
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, but you ate something, it's the same idea
as eating it on שבת. Shabbat. So basically his point though is
that this is where you get into the nuances of punishments. So
there's כרת karet and then there's מיתה בידי שמים. mita bidei shamayim.
So it's actually different, although יום כיפור Yom Kippur you die, but
on שבת Shabbat let's say you did מלאכה melakha on שבת, Shabbat,
let's say you did מלאכה melakha on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, you
die but one is כרת karet and the other maybe מיתה בידי
שמים. mita bidei shamayim. So the point being though that you may
have thought, because the laws aren't necessarily spelled out, right, specifically in
terms of what you do for תשלומין, tashlumin, you may have thought,
okay fine, maybe what applies in כרת karet may not necessarily apply
in מיתה בידי שמים mita bidei shamayim cases because we do understand
that there's a idea of קים ליה בדרבה מיניה, kam lei be-drabba
minei, but does it apply in all cases of מיתה? mita? So
הרקנוס בן הקנס Harkonus ben Hakanas says yes. So whether שבת, Shabbat,
whether כיפור, Kippur, he makes יום כיפור Yom Kippur like שבת. Shabbat.
יום כיפור Yom Kippur is, if you will, like a slightly less
stringent one, it could be... You don't get death by בית דין.
Beit Din. Right. So it's like שבת Shabbat which has a higher
level, if you will. So he says it's all the same. So
קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei be-drabba minei. So too the point
being that because let's say he ate it במזיד, be-mezid, which is
the case we're talking about right now, so if he ate it
במזיד be-mezid it's מיתה בידי שמים, mita bidei shamayim, it's not actually
כרת karet if I eat תרומה trumah deliberately. So it's the same
idea. So it doesn't make a difference, it's like כרת, karet, מיתה
בידי שמים, mita bidei shamayim, it's all מיתה בידי שמים, mita bidei
shamayim, כרת, karet, either way, קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei be-drabba
minei. Which wasn't necessarily explicit from the פסוקים pesukim is what I'm
trying to say in all cases. So he's saying yes, we do
apply קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei be-drabba minei. That we take
that for granted, but the גמרא Gemara was working that out over
here that we do say קים ליה בדרבה מיניה kam lei be-drabba
minei in all those cases, whether it be כרת, karet, whether it
be מיתה בידי שמים. mita bidei shamayim. That's basically what this is
saying. So yes, we knew the conclusion, but the גמרא Gemara was
just getting us to that conclusion. So that's the point. So basically
we're saying it could still be רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGelili,
which is why בשוגג you pay him back, במזיד be-mezid you don't
because קים ליה בדרבה מיניה. kam lei be-drabba minei. And as a
matter of fact, as the גמרא Gemara? often likes to do, we're
saying this is כתנאי, ketanai, אוכל תרומת חמץ בפסח פטור מן התשלומין
ומדמי עצים okhel trumat chametz be-Pesach patur min ha-tashlumim u-mi-d'mei etzim דברי
רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. So if I eat this חמץ chametz?
stuff when I'm not supposed to, and I eat it on פסח
Pesach, and I'm not even a כהן, kohen, פטור
מן התשלומין ומדמי עצים, patur min ha-tashlumim u-mi-d'mei etzim, I don't pay
it back, דברי רבי עקיבא. divrei Rabbi Akiva. רבי יוחנן בן נורי
מחייב. Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri mechayev. רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan
ben Nuri says no, you're מחייב. mechayev. So then אמר לו רבי
עקיבא לרבי יוחנן בן נורי, amar lo Rabbi Akiva le-Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, so we're gonna have a little conversation over here. So רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said to רבי יוחנן בן נורי, Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, וכי מה הנאה יש לו בה?
ve-chi ma hana'ah yesh
lo bah? What kind of הנאה hana'ah can you get? I mean,
isn't חמץ בפסח Chametz be-Pesach worthless? אמר לו רבי יוחנן בן נורי
לרבי עקיבא, amar lo Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri le-Rabbi Akiva, מה הנאה
יש לאוכל תרומה טמאה בשאר כל השנה?
ma hana'ah yesh l'okhel trumah
t'mei'ah bish'ar kol ha-shanah? So okay, I'll answer to you, and what
about the rest of the year? The rest of the year if
I eat it בשוגג, I still have to pay him back, and
as we explained, as we said in the very top, no matter
how I use it, if I eat it, I drink it, if
it's טהור, tahor, if it's טמא, tamei, if it's טמא tamei I
still have to pay him back, you know you can't... even if
it's תרומה trumah that's טמא. tamei. And nevertheless I still have to
repay him. So you're getting all worked up over פסח, Pesach, what
about the rest of the year? So I say it makes no
difference. שמשלם לו, shemeshaleim lo, so why should that be any different?
אמר לו amar lo no, you said בתרומה טמאה bitrumah tmeiah בשאר
ימות השנה, bish'ar yemot hashanah, I can still find you a reason
why I should pay him back even if he used תרומה טמאה
trumah tmeiah the rest of the year. שאף על פי שאין לו
בה היתר אכילה יש לו בה היתר הסקה.
she'af al pi she'ein lo
bah heter achilah yeish lo bah heter hasakah. You're allowed to use
it for firewood according to everybody, you're allowed to use תרומה טמאה
trumah tmeiah for firewood. Or for fuel, I shouldn't say firewood, I
mean תרומה trumah isn't wood, let's say he took oil, and
I use the oil to burn something, use it for a
candle, right? It can
be wood. What did you say? You take a תרומה trumah. olive
and plant it, it turns into an olive tree, the wood is
תרומה. trumah Oh, okay. Right, but I'm talking right, okay. Fair enough.
Fair enough, right, not the usual case. תאמר בזה שאין לו בה
לא היתר אכילה ולא היתר הסקה? tomar bezeh she'ein lo bah lo
heter achilah velo heter hasakah? You're going to okay, the rest of
the year I can at least use the תרומה trumah, for something,
but what can I use תרומת חמץ chametz. for? Nothing. I mean,
this that he's going according to the opinion that says you can't
use it at all. I can't use it for anything.
So הא למה זה
דומה? ha lemah zeh domeh? It's like תרומת תותים וענבים שנטמאו, trumat
tutim va'anavim shenitma'u, שאין בהן לא היתר אכילה ולא היתר הסקה. she'ein
bahen lo heter achilah velo heter hasakah. So basically stuff isn't so
good for firewood because it's very moist is what they're saying. So
fruit and you certainly can't eat it, and it wouldn't even be
worth anything for firewood. So that's what I compare it to. Okay,
basically so that's that argument, right? So one says yes, the other
says no. So that's what we're saying over here. So that's so
you may say that it may refer to our earlier מחלוקת machloket
as which we have now gotten out of, about about תרומה, trumah
is it לפי מדה? lefi middah? Remember, that's what we tried to
cite it. Is it לפי מדה lefi middah or is it לפי
דמים? So we ended up we started out by saying I understand
why if it's according to a quantity, but if it's according to
a value, then why? Then we said no, this is the opinion
that holds it still does have value. Okay, then we tried to
explain this like תנאים. tanna'im. Does it have value or does it
not? Fine. Okay. במה דברים אמורים? bameh devarim amurim? Now we're going
to further caveat this because remember, we're not talking just about חמץ
chametz, stuff, but we're basically talking about תרומה trumah in general, but
now but we're still in terms of חמץ. chametz במפריש תרומה והחמיצה.
bemafresh trumah vehichmitzah. So okay, so now when did it become חמץ?
chametz If let's say I think about wheat, right? So I gave
him תרומה trumah from my wheat, which is what you do. And
then it became חמץ. chametz Or, you can just say even before
פסח, Pesach like I gave it from תרומה trumah, that was already
חמץ, chametz. which you're allowed to do too. Basically we're saying is
you did it at a time when פסח Pesach didn't come along
and make it valueless. So he's saying במה דברים אמורים במפריש תרומה
והחמיצה. bameh devarim amurim bemafresh trumah vehichmitzah. אבל מפריש תרומת חמץ, aval
mafresh trumat chametz, if like at the very onset I gave it
I gave on, took it from חמץ chametz at a time where
I shouldn't have דברי הכל אינה קדושה. divrei hakol einah kdushah. Then
it doesn't even become תרומה, trumah. right? So because well, actually we
didn't say why, but but basically we're going to explain it now.
תניא אידך. tanya idach. תניא אידך tanya idach is basically going to
explain it. ונתן לכהן את הקודש. venatan lacohein et hakodesh. That's what
it says in תרומה. trumah, דבר הראוי להיות קודש, davar hara'uy lihyot
kodesh, something that could be קודש kodesh or should be even פרט
לאוכל תרומת חמץ בפסח שפטור מן התשלומין ומדמי עצים, p'rat le'ochel trumat
chametz bePesach shepatur min hatashlumin umidmei eitzim, דברי רבי אלעזר בן יעקב.
divrei Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. So that will exclude something from if
you ate תרומת חמץ chametz בפסח because it's פטור מן התשלומין ומדמי
עצים patur min hatashlumin umidmei eitzim because he's holding basically that it
is valueless. So since חמץ chametz, can't become תרומה, terumah so so
you're exempt. So that's רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov.
רבי אלעזר חסמא, Rabbi Elazar Chisma, רבי אלעזר חסמא Rabbi Elazar Chisma
I guess, from חסמא Chisma is מחייב. mechayev. So he says no,
I don't care, you're still חייב. chayav. So now again the same
conversation. אמר לו רבי אלעזר חסמא לרבי אלעזר בן יעקב, amar lo
Rabbi Elazar Chisma leRabbi Elazar ben Yaakov, מה הנאה יש לו לאוכל
תרומה טמאה בשאר ימות השנה שמשלם לו? mah hana'ah yeish lo le'ochel
trumah tmeiah bish'ar yemot hashanah shemeshaleim lo? So he says okay, take
the rest of the year, you still have to repay even if
it's תרומה טמאה. trumah tmeiah. So so too for פסח Pesach. you
have to repay. אמר לו לא, אם אמרת בתרומה טמאה בשאר ימות
השנה שאף על פי שאין לו בה היתר אכילה יש לו בה
היתר הסקה.
amar lo lo, im amarta bitrumah tmeiah bish'ar yemot hashanah she'af al
pi she'ein
lo bah heter achilah yeish lo bah heter hasakah. Too much, you
can't compare תרומה terumah for the rest of the year that's טמאה
temeiah to תרומה terumah,
on תרומת חמץ chametz on פסח.
Pesach The rest of the year even though it's טמאה temeiah and
you can't eat it, you can still use it. תאמר בזו Tomar
b'zo on פסח Pesach. שאין לו בה לא היתר אכילה ולא היתר
הסקה
she'ein lo ba lo
heter achilah v'lo heter hasakah because it's useless on פסח. Pesach, אמר
לו אף בזו יש לו בה היתר הסקה.
Amar lo af b'zo yesh
lo ba heter hasakah. No, I still, you can still use it.
Basically, he's holding like that opinion that says you're allowed to use
it or you can have הנאה. hana'ah. שאם מצאו כהן מריטא פני
כבואו מסיקה תחת תבשילו. She'im matza'o kohen m'reita fney k'vo'o masikah tachat
tavshilo. You're allowed to have הנאה. hana'ah. I can't eat it, but
I can give it to my dog or I can use it
for firewood. So basically that's what it comes down to. The first
opinion is holding that it's valueless and the second opinion is holding
no, you're still allowed to have הנאה hana'ah from it, in which
case then they have to repay. All right, עמוד ב׳. Amud Bet.
אמר אביי: Amar Abaye רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, רבי עקיבא, רבי יוחנן
בן נורי, כולם סבירא להו חמץ של פסח אסור בהנאה.
Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov, Rabbi Akiva, Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri, kulam sevira
lehu chametz shel
Pesach assur b'hana'ah. So all these other people disagreed. I mean, we
had a whole bunch of מחלוקות machlokot there but if you're keeping
track of the names, but basically the other side of all this
equation, those disagreed and said you're פטור patur from תשלומים tashlumim and
it has no הנאה. hana'ah. All these people are holding חמץ של
פסח אסור בהנאה. chametz shel Pesach assur b'hana'ah. It's a pretty big
group there. Yeah. ובהא פליגי דרבי עקיבא סבר לפי דמים משלם ויוחנן
בן נורי סבר לפי מדה משלם. U'veha pligi d'Rabbi Akiva savar l'fi
damim meshalem v'Yochanan ben Nuri savar l'fi midah meshalem. So again, there's
a lot to keep track of over there but remember what started
this
whole thing was whether
you pay according to the value or according to the quantity. So
the point being then
that so Rabbi Akiva,
so they're saying is that although Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yochanan ben
Nuri, which we were just explaining a second ago, you may even
be able to hold that as we were explaining before, the way
I was trying to explain it was, oh yeah, one side of
the equation is it's valueless, the other side because תורה Torah takes
it out of your jurisdiction. Others say no, you're not even allowed
to use it as firewood. But again, what we could have said
is that it's a מחלוקת, machloket, that I took whatever it is
of חמץ chametz. and I have to give back whatever it is
because vis-a-vis the law of תרומה, terumah right? Again, I have to
make the law whole and I have to repay it. Remember that
that was the other way we could have said it. I don't
really care, value or not, I still have to repay. So רבי
עקיבא סבר לפי דמים משלם ויוחנן בן נורי סבר לפי מדה משלם.
Rabbi Akiva savar l'fi damim meshalem v'Yochanan ben Nuri savar l'fi midah
meshalem. So let me just go back for just one second over
here and because remember Rabbi Akiva and Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri had
a מחלוקת, machloket, right? And Rabbi Akiva says you're פטור. patur. Rabbi
Yochanan ben Nuri says you're חייב. chayav. And then they went to
this whole argument back and forth. What about the rest of the
year? And then I hold that nevertheless you still have to repay.
And then he says oh, it's like eating like the תרומה trumah
of berries that became טמא. tamei. There's like no value at all,
right? So again, as I mentioned, you could say that it's a
מחלוקת machloket as to whether or not it has value. One side
holds that you have to pay, says it does have value. The
other side that holds you don't have to pay holds it has
no value. Just what we were trying to say. But you could
have said even all these people nevertheless can all hold it's אסור
בהנאה assur b'hana'ah and ובהא פליגי u'veha pligi that it's whether you
do according to the value or according to the מדה. midah. If
you do according to the value, okay, it has no value on
חמץ. chametz Taking that more accepted opinion that חמץ של פסח chametz
shel Pesach is valueless. So it has no value, that's why you
don't have to pay anything. But Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri says no,
I pay according to the quantity. I took a quantity of I
took a liter of oil, I give back a liter of oil.
So okay, so that's and that's what we tried to say, we
make this a מחלוקת תנאים, machloket Tanna'im, right? So פשיטא, Pshita, if
we're trying to make it to a מחלוקת תנאים machloket Tanna'im then
we're bringing these תנאים Tanna'im of course, that's why אמר אביי is
saying it. So no, as I was saying, it's not so פשוט.
pashut. מהו דתימא רבי יוחנן בן נורי כנמי כרבי עקיבא סבירא ליה
דאמר לפי דמים משלם.
Ma'u d'teima Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri
k'nami k'Rabbi Akiva sevira leh d'amar l'fi damim meshalem. You may say
no, they're not talking about whether you took a quantity or דמים.
And even according to the one that says it's דמים, right? In
which case it should be worthless, like that's what Rabbi Akiva says,
it's worthless. Even then maybe Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri is saying that
והכא היינו טעמא דקמיחייב משום דסבר לה כרבי יוסי הגלילי דאמר חמץ
של פסח מותר בהנאה. v'hacha hainu ta'ama d'kamichayev mishum d'savar lah k'Rabbi
Yossi HaGlili d'amar chametz shel Pesach mutar b'hana'ah. Because he holds like
רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yossi HaGlili, according to that position that says
it's מותר בהנאה. mutar b'hana'ah. So yes, it's not I still am
talking about a case he may reply that. That that we're talking
about value, but it's not worthless like we've been saying all along
that there's one opinion that says exactly that, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that not. קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that he's
that that they're not holding like רבי יוסי הגלילי. Rabbi Yose HaGlili.
Everyone says it's worthless, but nevertheless, this is aligning according to the
opinions that we said before, that if if you're focusing strictly on
if you're focusing strictly on value and we hold like the commonly
accepted principal opinion that goes the commonly accepted view that we don't
go that we don't allow הנאה hana'ah from חמץ chametz on פסח,
Pesach, then it is worthless. Nevertheless, even even if even the other
side would say, even if we go according to the opinion that
says that we don't allow you to have הנאה hana'ah from פסח,
Pesach, it just a law of תרומה Trumah, essentially. I took a
liter, I give back a liter, which is what we were saying
in the very beginning before before we introduced all this. Okay, but
the question is ואימא הכי נמי. v'eima hachi nami. So how how
do you know it doesn't hold like רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose
HaGlili? That's a good point, right? Because you're saying oh, yeah, okay,
all these people, they really hold it that it's אסור בהנאה, assur
b'hana'ah, and they don't hold like רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili,
right? Well okay, how do you know? Maybe he does hold like
רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose HaGlili? And maybe it's nothing to do
with מידה, and you know, I mean maybe it's nothing maybe דמים,
you know, maybe forget that. Maybe he holds like רבי יוסי הגלילי,
Rabbi Yose HaGlili, it has value, I have to repay him. So
אם כן, im ken, הדר ליה hadar leh רבי יוחנן בן נורי
Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri who disagreed
and there was all this back and forth, he should have answered
כהיכא דהדר ליה k'heicha d'hadar leh רבי אלעזר חסמא Rabbi Elazar Chisma
to רבי אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. So now remember,
we brought in and I glossed over it just a little bit,
we brought in two מחלוקתים machloketim and then there's the מחלוקת machloket
of רבי יוחנן בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri and רבי עקיבא,
Rabbi Akiva, and then later on we sort of had the same
מחלוקת machloket later at the very bottom of the עמוד ב' amud
bet, of רבי אלעזר חסמא, Rabbi Elazar Chisma, right, and and רבי
אלעזר בן יעקב. Rabbi Elazar ben Yaakov. Now they seem to be
the same, they seem to be the same, but at the end
he says, just look at just turn to the עמוד ב', because
he says שאם רצה כהן ירענו לפני
כלבו ומסיקו תחת תבשילו, she'im ratza Kohen
yira'enu lifnei
kalbo u'masiko tachat tavshilo,
right? You can give it to your dog or use it as
firewood. So he didn't say, the מחלוקת machloket between רבי יוחנן בן
נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva did not
say that. He says אף על פי שאין לו היתר אכילה יש
לו היתר הסקה תאמר בזה שאין לו בו היתר אכילה והיתר הסקה.
af al pi she'ein lo heter achilah yesh lo heter hachakah tomar
b'zeh she'ein lo bo heter achilah
v'heter hachakah. So he says למה זה דומה לתרומת תותים וענבים שנטמאו
שאין לו היתר אכילה והיתר הסקה. l'mah zeh domeh l'trumat tutim v'anavim
she'nitm'u she'ein lo heter achilah v'heter hachakah. So it sounds it really
sounds the same, but it's
not exactly the same.
So what we're trying to say is he doesn't say that he
doesn't say it's it's so similar, but it's not identical. So and
most of this is and a lot of this is also interpolation.
But the point is he didn't say he didn't
say exactly that, the way you're allowed to do that ירענו לפני
כלבו ומסיקו תחת תבשילו, yira'enu lifnei kalbo u'masiko tachat tavshilo,
he should have he should have said that.
I mean it seems maybe we should look at רש"י Rashi over
here if he said if he says anything. Because does it say
anything? אף וזה יש לו היתר הסקה. af v'zeh yesh lo heter
hachakah. He says even with this יש לו היתר הסקה. yesh lo
heter hachakah. But he but what the problem is he does say
that, doesn't he? Maybe I'm missing something here. I thought he did
say that, right? I think maybe what it's saying is I think
that's the point that he does the whole last line in the
second מחלוקת machloket is saying that really you can do the כהן
Kohen can do something with it, so you can get some sort
of הנאה hana'ah with it.
But for the fact that in the first מחלוקת machloket רבי יוחנן
בן נורי Rabbi Yochanan ben Nuri doesn't respond with that response, so
therefore he thinks he agrees
with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
that there's in no case can
you ever get הנאה hana'ah from it because it's always אסור. assur.
Nevertheless, he still thinks that you should be חייב chayav in something
because he goes by מידה.
But he still agrees with רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that in no
scenario can you ever get. No, but didn't he say didn't he
say שאף על פי שאין לו, she'af al pi she'ein lo, he
does say שאף על פי שאין לו בה היתר אכילה יש לו
בה היתר הסקה.
she'af al pi she'ein lo bah heter achilah yesh
lo bah heter hachakah. He came out and said that, didn't he?
Where did he say that? Wasn't that wasn't that in the גמרא?
Gemara Right, but then רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva comes back and says
no, it doesn't have anything, and then he doesn't respond after that
as opposed to the second מחלוקת machloket where there is a response.
Okay, maybe that yeah. Okay, so he should have said there is
something, so therefore since he didn't say that, so therefore since he
didn't say that. So there must be that he holds that there
is no value to it, in which case then why would he
still obligate you to pay? So it must be that it's not
a matter of value that we pay תרומה, Trumah. but rather it's
a value, it's a matter of a quantity. I took a quantity
and I repay a quantity. So it's not whether it has value
or not. So you have to apologize to them. My daughter was,
my daughter kept me up till 2:30 in the morning. She wasn't
feeling well, so I was like this is the night before I
was like I'm falling asleep preparing this.
So תנו רבנן: Tanu Rabbanan: אוכל
כזית תרומה משלם קרן וחומש. Ochel kezayis Trumah meshallem keren v'chomesh. This
is now, now forget about חומש chomesh for the moment. Now we're
just getting to just regular תרומה. Trumah, I eat, as we mentioned
all along, אוכל כזית תרומה משלם קרן וחומש. ochel kezayis Trumah meshallem
keren v'chomesh. I eat a כזית kezayis of תרומה, Trumah, I have
to pay back the value and then you have to pay back
a fifth. אבא שאול אומר עד שיהא בו שוה פרוטה. Abba Shaul
omer: Ad sheyehei bo shaveh perutah. So he's saying that yes, that's
true, but usually most things are שיעורים, shiurim, right? Like I have
to eat a כותבת הגסה koseves hagagasah on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
right? I eat a כזית kezayis of תרומה, Trumah right? But he's
saying, and now we're going to try to understand whether it's a
כזית kezayis and שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah or just שוה פרוטה. shaveh
perutah. So forget about my volume, I should say, for a moment,
but does it have value? Right? Let's say it's like a really,
you know, stale olive or whatever it is, you know, you couldn't
do much with. So he's saying that there's, and we're going to
try to understand whether it's an additional caveat or just one caveat.
The point being though, it has to be worth something.
It has to be worth something.
So let's say my זית zayis isn't worth a זית, zayis, so
to speak, right? So it's let's say I ate a worthless זית,
zayis, like I said, like let's say it's, you know, whatever, stale,
spoiled, whatever, right? And it's not worth anything, then I don't have
to pay the קרן karen. וחומש. That's let's go with that for
now. No, well this opinion, the first opinion says I do. I
mean this is a כזית, kezayis, I have to repay the קרן
karen and I have to pay חומש. chomesh. I pay on the
כזית kezayis and you know, a fifth essentially, or really a כזית
kezayis and a quarter, but the point is that he's saying I
do, the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, which is not attributed to anybody,
but אבא שאול Abba Shaul is saying it has to be worth
something.
If it's not worth anything, then no.
Okay. מאי טעמא תנא קמא? Mai ta'ama Tanna Kamma? So אמר קרא:
amar kra: ואיש כי
יאכל
קדש בשגגה.
ve'ish ki
yochal
kodesh bishgagah. He focuses on the אכילה. achilah.
If you eat קדש בשגגה kodesh bishgagah and אכילה achilah is in
general the minimum אכילה, achilah, I mean you know, אכילה achilah can
obviously be more than a כזית, kezayis, but אכילה achilah at a
minimum is a כזית. kezayis. So by weight or by money? This
is by volume. By volume? Yeah. Not שוה. Not שוה, no, that's
the second opinion. Okay. The תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says I eat
an olive, I give, I have to, basically he's like basically he's
like the מדה midah kind of thing, right? And and but the
point is he says you know we didn't yet know how big
a מדה, midah, right? We were dealing with it in the abstract
as in you know I was saying like a liter. But now
we're saying what the minimum is, what the threshold is. The minimum
is a כזית kezayis because it says ואיש כי יאכל קדש בשגגה,
ish ki yochal kodesh bishgagah, and although it says קדש kodesh it's
talking about תרומה Trumah. by the way, not הקדש, hekdesh, I know
it's similar but it's תרומה. Trumah So it's viewed as a minimum
of a זית. zayis. Okay. ואבא שאול Ve'Abba Shaul who's the opposite
view, not opposite but the opposing view, is is saying that never
forget forget my volume for a moment, it
has to be worth something because that's
the end of it. ואיש כי יאכל קדש בשגגה, ve'ish ki yochal
kodesh bishgagah, that's the whole פסוק pasuk over here.
Does the ספרא Sifra quote it?
I should really view it, read it and where is it? 22:14.
Yeah. Because he's
quoting the end of the פסוק. pasuk. I don't want
to get it wrong.
I'll read it here. ואיש כי יאכל קדש בשגגה ויסף חמשיתו עליו.
ve'ish ki yochal kodesh bishgagah veyasaf chamishito alav. Yeah, I did know
it. If you eat this קדש, kodesh,
which is all talking about תרומה Trumah, by the way because the
whole thing is תרומה, Terumah then ויסף חמשיתו עליו veyasaf chamishito alav
and you have to give back the fifth. So the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma was really focused on the first part of יאכל yochal
which is an אכילה, achilah, but ונתן לכהן את הקדש, venasan l'kohen
es hakodesh, that's the end of it. And you give the כהן
kohen the קדש. kodesh. So אמר קרא: amar kra: ונתן, venasan, ואין
נתינה פחות משוה פרוטה. ve'ein nesinah pachus mishaveh perutah. other places where
we have ונתן, v'natan, נתינה, netinah, giving something is not considered as
if you gave him anything if it's not worth anything. So it's
not considered a giving, if you will, if it's at least if
at least it's worth a פרוטה. perutah. If it's worth, you know,
that's considered a giving, if it's not worth a פרוטה perutah it's
not considered a giving. It has to be worth at least a
פרוטה. perutah. So okay, so now the question's going to be what
does each one do with the other part, right? So ואידך, v'idach,
so אבא שאול Abba Shaul who focused on the נתינה, netina, what
does he do with the יאכל? yochal? הכתיב יאכל! haktiv yochal! What
does he do with that, which the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma learned
is a כזית? kezait? So ההוא פרט למזיק הוא דאתא. hahu prat
l'mazik hu d'ata. He's saying, oh no, let's say I damaged it,
I didn't eat it. Then I don't have to pay the additional
fifth. I still have to pay it, you know, like whatever, like
I squashed it, now it's worthless, so I pay back just the
קרן karen and not the חומש. chomesh. So that's what that's coming
to tell you, יאכל. yochal. יאכל's yochal not coming to teach you
how much I need to eat, the minimum value, it's coming to
tell you דווקא davka eating and not destroying it in other ways.
תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, what about תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who says
it's a כזית's kezait worth and what does he do with ונתן?
v'natan? הכתיב ונתן haktiv v'natan from which אבא שאול Abba Shaul learned
it has to be a value, what does he... how does he
get out of that? ההוא מיבעי ליה לדבר הראוי להיות קודש. hahu
miba'ei leh l'davar hara'uy lihyot kodesh. So that has to be something
that can be קודש, kodesh, as opposed to let's say then our
חמץ stuff that you know we said that that's only if he
only did it before let's say while it was still wheat and
didn't become חמץ, or if I did it you know from חמץ
actually before פסח, Pesach you know, then they can do it but
not if I gave it on פסח Pesach. from חמץ. Okay, that's
what it's coming to tell you. It has to tell you ונתן
v'natan that I only have to repay it either if it's something
that can become holy or I can only repay it with something
that can become holy. So let's say you know I took his
whatever his olives, I ate his olives, right, and now I want
to
repay him with חמץ on פסח. Pesach, No, I can't do it.
So that's what it's coming to tell you, it has to... I
have to give him back something that's worth something. Or the opposite
would be if he eats חמץ on פסח, something like that. Right,
that's... that's the question, right. But anyway the point being though it
has to be you know something that's in the פרשה. parsha. If
I broaden the scope, it has to be something that's in the
פרשה, parsha, not something that just you know they can't. And remember
as רש"י Rashi explained like when I give him back the value
and a fifth, I'm not actually paying him, that's the whole point,
I'm giving him actually in kind, I'm giving him back produce. I
don't know if it has to be exactly the bread but like
you know I took his bread of תרומה and I gave him
back like apples, whatever, but something in the food world. Okay, תנו
רבנן, tanu rabbanan, let's try to get a little further. האוכל תרומה
פחות מכזית משלם את הקרן ואינו משלם את החומש. ha'ochel terumah pachot
mikezait meshalem et hakaren v'eino meshalem et hachomesh. So I eat less
than a כזית, kezait, משלם את הקרן ואינו משלם את החומש. meshalem
et hakaren v'eino meshalem et hachomesh. היכי דמי? heichi dami? What kind
of case is this? אי דאית ביה שוה פרוטה, ei d'it beh
shaveh perutah, because you know let's say this is a real value,
you know, really valuable little piece of olive that I took... or
whatever it is I took, you know, it was very valuable, it
doesn't have to be an olive, but just... make... it's whatever I
took was less than a כזית kezait but it's very valuable, it's
worth something. Or not. אי דלית ביה שוה פרוטה, ei d'leit beh
shaveh perutah, let's say it's not worth something, so it's not so
valuable. קרן נמי לא לשלם. karen nami lo lishalem. If I didn't...
if it's less than a כזית, kezait, right, that's our case, and
it's not worth a פרוטה, perutah, remember the ruling was I only
repay the קרן. karen So if it's not worth anything and it's
less than a כזית, kezait, so I shouldn't pay anything. קרן נמי
לא לשלם. karen nami lo lishalem. What have I done? ואי דאית
ביה שוה פרוטה, v'ei d'it beh shaveh perutah, so and if it
is a שוה פרוטה's shaveh perutah worth, then חומש נמי לשלם. chomesh
nami lishalem. So why... so I don't
get it, so why
am I only paying קרן karen. and not חומש, chomesh, right? I
should pay nothing or I should pay everything, everything being the קרן
and the חומש. chomesh. So לעולם דאית ביה שוה פרוטה, l'olam d'it
beh shaveh perutah, no it's actually worth a פרוטה. perutah. ואפילו הכי
כיון דלית ביה כזית משלם את הקרן ואינו משלם את החומש.
v'afillu hachi keivan d'leit beh kezait meshalem et hakaren v'eino meshalem
et hachomesh. So since it's not... since it doesn't have a כזית,
kezait, then I pay the קרן and I don't pay the חומש.
chomesh. Now who would you say this goes like? Remember we had
this מחלוקת macheloket between the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and אבא שאול,
Abba Shaul, right? The one that... the one that focused on value...
there's the one that focused on value which is... and there's the
one that focused on quantity. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma focused on quantity
and אבא שאול Abba Shaul focused on value. So you'd say this
is not like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, right? Because אבא שאול Abba
Shaul focused on value, so he doesn't care... he doesn't care what
the quantity is. If it's worth a פרוטה, perutah, you know, that's
what you need to do. We decided that this is a case,
right? We couldn't understand it at all if it's not... if it's
not worth anything and if it's not big enough. So we said
all right, it has to at least be worth a פרוטה. perutah.
So oh, because it's not כזית, kezait, then I have to pay
back the קרן. It's not like אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. אבא שאול
Abba Shaul would say, if he's a value guy, I took a
value. Oh, תנא קמא Tanna Kamma I understand. תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma,
you know, he's focused on so let's see how it works. אמרונה
קמיה דרב פפא. Amruna kamei deRav Papa. היכי דלמא כאבא שאול? Hechei
dilma keAbba Shaul? אי כאבא שאול Iy keAbba Shaul אמר כיון שיש
בו שוה פרוטה amar kevan sheyesh bo shaveh perutah אף על גב
דלית ביה כזית. af al gav d'leit beh kezayit. אמר להו רב
פפא Amar lehu Rav Papa אפילו תימא אבא שאול afilu teima Abba
Shaul אבא שאול תרתי בעי. Abba Shaul tarti ba'ei. He needs both.
Ah, okay. So he needs he needs the value and he needs
the size. So since this isn't the right size although it is
the right value, then you know then you still have to repay.
So I'm sorry this yeah, so we've established we established the case
that it is שוה פרוטה. shaveh perutah. So it's the right value
but it's still not the right size. So I still took something
of value but nevertheless the דין din of חומש chomesh he's saying
is something that you know that has to do also with size.
So basically the point being he requires both. So the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma certainly we know requires size and we established that this
is a case that you don't you're not a maximum size. So
therefore I'm not paying the fine. So אבא שאול Abba Shaul also
although he requires value and you have it here he also requires
size. So both the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma and אבא שאול Abba
Shaul would say you don't have to pay back the additional חומש
chomesh because you don't have the right size. ומי בעי אבא שאול
תרתי? Umi ba'ei Abba Shaul tarti? Does he really require both? והתנן
אבא שאול אומר את שיש בו שוה פרוטה חייב בתשלומין את שאין
בו שוה פרוטה אינו חייב בתשלומין.
Veha'tenan Abba Shaul omer et sheyesh bo shaveh perutah chayav betashlumin
et she'ein bo shaveh perutah eino chayav betashlumin. So he we learned
already he says that if it's שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah and this
is expanding what we said before, if it is שוה פרוטה shaveh
perutah then חייב בתשלומין chayav betashlumin and if not if it's not
worth a שוה פרוטה shaveh perutah if it's not the equivalent monetary
worth of a פרוטה perutah אינו חייב בתשלומין. eino chayav betashlumin. אמרו
לו לא אמרו שוה פרוטה אלא לענין מעילה בלבד. Amru lo lo
amru shaveh perutah ella inyan me'ilah bilvad. So no when are we
all worried about שוה פרוטה? shaveh perutah? That's for מעילה me'ilah stuff.
אבל לתרומה אינו חייב עד שיהיה בו כזית. Aval litrumah eino chayav
ad sheyehei bo kezayit. It's only until you have a כזית. kezayit.
Now it seems already that the battle lines are pretty clear. אבא
שאול Abba Shaul is just saying פרוטה perutah and they're just saying
a כזית. kezayit. ואי איתא כיון שיש בו כזית מיבעי ליה. Ve'im
ita kevan sheyesh bo kezayit miba'ei lei. And now if and if
basically what he's saying is that you know that really אבא שאול
Abba Shaul as you see really it's one or the other. I
mean you know I mean it's pretty clear. It's basically what the
גמרא is saying. You know then they should've you know like the
whole מחלוקת machlokes would've been different. You wouldn't have said one or
the other. It's not he would've said oh yeah no it's this
and that. They're not going that way. It's clear battle lines, basically
what they're saying. So תיובתא. tiyuvta. It is תיובתא. tiyuvta. So he's
been disproven. ואף רב פפא Ve'af Rav Papa who's the one that
said this all this that he requires both, ואף רב פפא הדר
ביה. af Rav Papa hadar beih. He too retracted his opinion and
really so everyone's saying it's one or the other. I'm just trying
to figure out if this is a good place to stop. It
probably is. It's already 8:30 and this is all yeah. Sorry for
that little brain freeze before.
Thanks. You
know
having
the
extended...